<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>FElf</name>
		<update version="0.3.0">
			<file name="race-FElf.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/araag2/Faleria-Aurora/master/user-faleria/beginners-guide/races/race-FElf.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="FElf" type="Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACE_FELF">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">"Far greater is the admiration I harbor for the elves than for any other type of mortal in this world of ours. Only the Gods could stand in my way, had I been gifted with an elven body at birth. I admit to be envious of their natural link with magic, even if most misuse it."
			<br />- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death</p>

			<p>The tall and slender elves were born into magic. Many are the elves that adore the finer things in life, such as silk, silver and adornments that connect them with the life around them. Due to their long life they may come off as uncaring, stagnant or even lazy, when in reality they just see the world in a completely different way than any other mortal could hope to.</p>

			<h4>ARCANE MASTERS</h4>
			<p>It's said that of the three primary Kassian races elves were the last to emerge in Faleria, being created alongside humans and dwarves by Yivor, Myllad and Kassia as servants in their godly works. Elves were created for Myllad, God of knowledge, magic and libraries, to serve in his vast library. Through the years, elves organized and catalogued his many scrolls and tomes and, sometimes, even conducted field research alongside humans.</p>

			<h4>ELF NAMES</h4>
			<p>Elven names are full of voiced sounds and tend to involve diphthongs, l's and r's. Examples of elven names are Hemcriel, Zavandriel and Emaria.</p>

			<h4>BROKEN PEOPLE</h4>
			<p>Elves had already settled in Faleria for many generations once the Great Penury broke out. During and after that period, some elven lineages turned to conquest while others sought to rebuild what was lost. This divide still shapes elven cultures today.</p>

			<h4>ELF TRAITS</h4>
            <p>Your elven character has certain characteristics in common with all other elves.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> Elves are 1,75-2 meters tall, average 68 kg and are humanoids. Elves reach adulthood at the age of 108 but are considered young until the age of 150. On average, they live about 500 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size and Speed.</em></strong> Your size is Medium and your base walking speed is 9 meters.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Elven Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by 1, or increase three different ability scores by 1. Your Intelligence score maximum is 22, instead of the normal 20.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Elven Darkvision.</em></strong> You can see in dim light within 18 meters of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it was dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gold.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Keen Senses.</em></strong> You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Researchers of Myllad.</em></strong> You have advantage on saving throws against exhaustion, and magic can't put you to sleep.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Elvish Rest.</em></strong> When performing a long rest, elves don't need to sleep. Instead, they can enter a meditative state for only 4 hours. The clear state of mind gained by meditating in this way grants you the ability to cast your Mortal Subtype's level 1 spell twice instead of once. You may instead rest for the normal 8 hours, which grants you 1d10 temporary hit points.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> Four subtypes are available: Dark Elves, Imperial Elves, Light Elves and Night Elves.</p>

			<p>See <a href="https://faleria.pt/mortal_type/elf">Website</a> for more details.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Elven Ability Score Improvement Option (FElf)" supports="Custom Ability Score Improvement Option" />
			<stat name="intelligence:max:extra" value="2" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_ABILITY_SCORE_MAXIMUM_OVER_20" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="9" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_ELVISH" />
			<select type="Language" name="Customized Language" supports="Custom Race Language" number="2" requirements="ID_FALERIA_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_RACE_ELF" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_KEEN_SENSES" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_RESEARCHERS_OF_MYLLAD" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_ELVISH_REST" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_SUBRACE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Keen Senses" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_KEEN_SENSES">
		<description>
			<p>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_PERCEPTION" requirements="!ID_FALERIA_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_PROFICIENCY" />
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Customized Skill Proficiency" supports="Skill" requirements="ID_FALERIA_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_PROFICIENCY" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<element name="Researchers of Myllad" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_RESEARCHERS_OF_MYLLAD">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on saving throws against exhaustion, and magic can't put you to sleep.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You have advantage on saving throws against exhaustion, and magic can't put you to sleep.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Elvish Rest" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_ELVISH_REST">
		<description>
			<p>When performing a long rest, elves don't need to sleep. Instead, they can enter a meditative state for only 4 hours. The clear state of mind gained by meditating in this way grants you the ability to cast your Mortal Subtype's level 1 spell twice instead of once. You may instead rest for the normal 8 hours, which grants you 1d10 temporary hit points.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can long rest in 4 hours by meditating, or rest 8 hours to gain 1d10 temporary hit points.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

    
	<element name="FElf Subrace" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FELF_SUBRACE">
		<description>
			<p>Four subtypes are available: Dark Elves, Imperial Elves, Light Elves and Night Elves.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Sub Race" name="FElf Subrace" supports="FElf" />
		</rules>
	</element>

    <!-- Elf Sub Races List-->

    <!-- Dark Elf Sub Race-->

    <element name="Dark Elf" type="Sub Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_SUB_RACE_DARK_ELF">
		<supports>FElf</supports>
		<description>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> <em>Dark Elves</em> are natural to the frozen tundras of Nyjörsa. They are often mistaken for dwarves in literature due to both being described as “ice-born” in silvanian, but physically they are very different. Like most elves, these are a tall and slender people, but dark elves tend to be the bulkiest of the elves. They have a distinct charcoal or dark blue skin, purple or pink eyes and silver white hair.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Shadowborn.</em></strong> You know the control flames cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the ice knife spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the darkness spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast ice knife or darkness with this trait, you can’t cast that spell again with it again until you finish a long rest.</p>

            <p class="indent">Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Facing Shadows.</em></strong> You have superior vision in dark and dim conditions. You can see in dim light within 36 meters of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of silver.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_RACE_DARK_ELF"/>
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_SUPERIORDARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DARK_ELF_MAGIC" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="Dark Elf Magic" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DARK_ELF_MAGIC">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <em>control flames</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>ice knife</em> spell this trait. When you reach 5th level, you can also cast the <em>darkness</em> spell with this trait. Once you cast <em>ice knife</em> or <em>darkness</em> with this trait, you can’t cast that spell again with it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You know the control flames cantrip. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
			<description level="3">You can cast ice knife once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
			<description level="5">You can cast darkness once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_CONTROL_FLAMES" level="1" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_ICE_KNIFE" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_DARKNESS" level="5" />
		</rules>
	</element>  

    <!-- Imperial Elf Sub Race-->

	<element name="Imperial Elf" type="Sub Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_SUB_RACE_IMPERIAL_ELF">
		<supports>FElf</supports>
		<description>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> <em>Imperial Elves</em> are closely related to light elves, directly deriving from them in “recent” times. Over the centuries, they have been raised only to serve the emperor. These elves have blonde or light brown hair, blue or green eyes and fair skin. Their ears are the longest of any elf, their length being a symbol of virtue, being adorned elegantly to show power or achievements.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Highborn.</em></strong> You know the <em>true strike</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>wrathful smite</em> spell and at 5th level the <em>crown of madness</em> spell with this trait, without requiring material components. Once you cast the <em>wrathful smite</em> or <em>crown of madness</em> spell with this trait, you can’t cast it again until you finish a long rest.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Imperial Training.</em></strong> You have proficiency with the shortsword, mace, shortbow and longbow.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_RACE_IMPERIAL_ELF"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_IMPERIAL_ELF_MAGIC" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_IMPERIAL_ELF_WEAPON_TRAINING" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="Imperial Elf Magic" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_IMPERIAL_ELF_MAGIC">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <em>true strike</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>wrathful smite</em> spell and at 5th level the <em>crown of madness</em> spell with this trait, without requiring material components. Once you cast the <em>wrathful smite</em> or <em>crown of madness</em> spell with this trait, you can’t cast it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
            <description>You know the true strike cantrip. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
            <description level="3">You can cast wrathful smite once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
            <description level="5">You can cast crown of madness once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_TRUE_STRIKE" level="1" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_WRATHFUL_SMITE" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_CROWN_OF_MADNESS" level="5" />
		</rules>
	</element>
    <element name="Imperial Elf Weapon Training" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_IMPERIAL_ELF_WEAPON_TRAINING">
		<description>
			<p>You have proficiency with the shortsword, mace, shortbow and longbow.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have proficiency with the shortsword, mace, shortbow and longbow.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SHORTSWORD" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_MACE" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_SHORTBOW" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_PROFICIENCY_LONGBOW" />
		</rules>
	</element>

    <!-- Light Elf -->

    <element name="Light Elf" type="Sub Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_SUB_RACE_LIGHT_ELF">
		<supports>FElf</supports>
		<description>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> <em>Light Elves</em> are the long lost cousins to the imperial elves. Natural to Scanduri, they are descendants of the elves that chose not to join the empire. These elves have brownish skin, brown or black hair, brown or black eyes and have the shortest ears of all elvish subtypes, with some being mistaken for Half-Elves. Despite their darker features, they call themselves light elves due to their enlightened decision to stay in Scanduri. Imperial elves only call them traitors.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Lightborn.</em></strong> You know the <em>light</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>faerie fire</em> spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the <em>invisibility</em> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast the <em>faerie fire</em> or <em>invisibility</em> spell with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Lightvision.</em></strong> You are immune to the blinded condition if it would be caused by light.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_RACE_LIGHT_ELF"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LIGHT_ELF_MAGIC" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LIGHT_ELF_LIGHTVISION" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="Light Elf Magic" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LIGHT_ELF_MAGIC">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <em>light</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>faerie fire</em> spell with this trait. Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the <em>invisibility</em> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast the <em>faerie fire</em> or <em>invisibility</em> spell with this trait, you can’t cast that spell with it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
            <description>You know the light cantrip. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
            <description level="3">You can cast faerie fire once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
            <description level="5">You can cast invisibility once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_LIGHT" level="1" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_FAERIE_FIRE" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_INVISIBILITY" level="5" />
		</rules>
	</element>
    <element name="Light Elf Lightvision" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LIGHT_ELF_LIGHTVISION">
		<description>
			<p>You are immune to the blinded condition if it would be caused by light.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You are immune to the blinded condition if it would be caused by light.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

    <!-- Night Elf -->

    <element name="Night Elf" type="Sub Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_SUB_RACE_NIGHT_ELF">
		<supports>FElf</supports>
		<description>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> <em>Night Elves</em> were the first elves to set foot in Faleria. Their purpose is lost to time, but now they remain in Manyhal. Having spent millenea in this world, their magic has attuned with the very nature that surrounds them. Their bodies have adapted to nature and transformed to resemble it. Their hair comes in almost any colour, as long as nature presents it. Their eyes either have a humanlike iris or an iris that covers their whole eye and these can be orange, yellow, brown, green or blue. Their skin has become a variation of the colour of tree trunks, so in a range from spruce to dark oak.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Oakborn.</em></strong> You know the <em>druidcraft</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>entangle</em> spell and at 5th level the <em>moonbeam</em> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast the entangle or moonbeam spell with this trait, you can’t cast it again until you finish a long rest.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ancestral Knowledge.</em></strong> You gain proficiency on a Wisdom skill of your choice..</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_RACE_NIGHT_ELF"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_NIGHT_ELF_MAGIC" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_NIGHT_ELF_ANCESTRAL_KNOWLEDGE" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="Night Elf Magic" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_NIGHT_ELF_MAGIC">
		<description>
			<p>You know the <em>druidcraft</em> cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the <em>entangle</em> spell and at 5th level the <em>moonbeam</em> spell with this trait, without requiring a material component. Once you cast the entangle or moonbeam spell with this trait, you can’t cast it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
            <description>You know the druidcraft cantrip. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
            <description level="3">You can cast entangle once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
            <description level="5">You can cast moonbeam once per long rest. Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma is your spellcasting ability for this spell when you cast it with this trait (choose when you select this mortal subtype).</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_DRUIDCRAFT" level="1" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_ENTANGLE" level="3" />
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_FALERIA_BG_SPELL_MOONBEAM" level="5" />
		</rules>
	</element>
    <element name="Night Elf Ancestral Knowledge" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_NIGHT_ELF_ANCESTRAL_KNOWLEDGE">
		<description>
			<p>You gain proficiency on a Wisdom skill of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You gain proficiency on a Wisdom skill of your choice.</description>
		</sheet>
        <rules>
			<select type="Proficiency" name="Skill Proficiency (Night Elf)" supports="Skill,Wisdom" number="1"/>
        </rules>
	</element>


</elements>
