<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Dwarf</name>
		<update version="0.3.3">
			<file name="race-dwarf.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/araag2/Faleria-Aurora/master/user-faleria/beginners-guide/races/race-dwarf.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Dwarf" type="Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACE_DWARF">
	<description>
			<p class="flavor">"Gran Caster Mezerys once told me that I should never underestimate a dwarfs skill, but I never quite understood him, until yesterday. I've been struggling to design a functional soul container for months. A single dwarf, Drugra Blaereus, did it in a day with only a piece of string, cobalt, ice and the sound of a cat's footsteps. His masterful prowess of the anvil could never be inferred from the way that he eats. After he was done, all he did was stroke his enormous red beard and gave me a satisfied look. His fine work will allow mine to flourish."
			<br />- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death</p>

			<p>The one thing dwarves love more than their trusty mounts is to forge. Many dwarven kingdoms have gotten rich out of selling items of imense value that they had crafted. Their usefulness makes them targets to kingdoms who are bold enough to think they can enslave them, while others forge alliances to gather their favour. Whatever may be the case, dwarves will only pay attention after they've had their 17th cup of ale.</p>

			<h4>CHILDREN OF THE FORGE</h4>
			<p>It is said that dwarves were one of the three primary Kássian races, the second to emerge in Faleria, being created alongside Humans and Elves by Yivor, Myllad and Kássia as servants in their godly works. Dwarves were created as payment to Yivor, the Smith, for his contribution in the creation of these mortals. Throughout many years, dwarves mined and polished the finest metals for Yivor's forge and, while performing their task, watched the great smith carefully, to learn his craft, while others chose to leave and settle in the many continents of Faleria.</p>

			<h4>WARHEARTS</h4>
			<p>While the Great Penury was underway, Yivor and his dwarves remained neutral to this mortal conflict. The other gods begged Yivor to lend them his aid but he didn't budge. Only the hand in marriage of Lypsosi, the Aspect of Lust, would sway him. After a vote, the gods decided the smiths help was too important to dismiss and gave in to his demands, in spite of Lypsosi's and Esnerel's protests. After the wedding ceremony, Yivor did keep his word. He forged three items for three legendary heroes and allowed his dwarves to go help in the war effort..</p>

			<h4>IRON AND STEEL</h4>
			<p>After the war, many dwarves lingered in Faleria, having found purpose and a new home. They bonded with other mortals and took their place in the world as the great masters of crafting. Their architecture, inspired by their creator, was sharp and rigid. They found themselves reinforced by their time serving Yivor, with better vision than most and a hardened body. They settled closest to the materials they needed, inside mountains and caves and grew communities around the ores that they would forge into art.</p>

			<h4>DWARF NAMES</h4>
			<p>Dwarves have a habit of rolling their tongue when they speak and that carries over to their names. It's hard to find a dwarf with no R, L or F in their name. Dwarven names can be Gundren, Forgen, Agalar and Lidsa, among others.</p>

			<h4>DWARF TRAITS</h4>
            <p>Your dwarf character has certain characteristics in common with all other dwarves.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong> Dwarves are 1,20-1,50 meters tall, average 68 kg and are humanoids. Dwarves reach adulthood at the age of 54 but are considered young until the age of 75. On average, they live about 250 years.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size and Speed.</em></strong> Your size is Medium and your base walking speed is 7.5 meters.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Dwarven Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by 1 or increase three different ability scores by 1. Your Constituiton score maximum is 22, instead of the normal 20.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Dwarven Darkvision.</em></strong> While underground, you can see in dim light within 18 meters of you as if it were bright light, and in darkness as if it was dim light. You can’t discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Dwarven Cunning.</em></strong> The dwarves learned a lot of Yilvor’s techniques while in his forge. While forging an item you can choose to substitute one of it’s ingredients for another of the same cost or rarity.</p>
			<p>Additionaly, while casting a spell that requires material components, you can choose to substitute one of it’s components for another of the same cost.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Tool Proficiency.</em></strong> You gain proficiency with one artisan’s tools of your choice from: smith’s tools, mason’s tools and cook’s utensils.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> Four subtypes are available: Forged Dwarves, Glacial Dwarves, Ironroot Dwarves and Monad Dwarves.</p>

			<p>See <a href="https://faleria.pt/mortal_type/dwarf">Website</a> for more details.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Dwarf Ability Score Improvement Option (Dwarf)" supports="Custom Ability Score Improvement Option" />
			<stat name="constitution:max:extra" value="2" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANTS_ABILITY_SCORE_MAXIMUM_OVER_20" />
			<stat name="innate speed" value="7.5" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_LEVISH" />
			<grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_RACE_DWARF" />
			<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DWARVEN_DARKVISION" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DWARF_DWARVEN_CUNNING" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DWARF_TOOL_PROFICIENCY" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DWARF_SUBRACE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Dwarven Cunning" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DWARF_DWARVEN_CUNNING">
		<description>
			<p><strong><em>Dwarven Cunning.</em></strong> The dwarves learned a lot of Yilvor’s techniques while in his forge. While forging an item you can choose to substitute one of it’s ingredients for another of the same cost or rarity.</p>
			<p>Additionaly, while casting a spell that requires material components, you can choose to substitute one of it’s components for another of the same cost.</p>
		</description>
        <sheet>
			<description>While forging an item you can choose to substitute one of it’s ingredients for another of the same cost or rarity. Additionally, while casting a spell that requires material components, you can choose to substitute one of it’s components for another of the same cost.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Tool Proficiency" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DWARF_TOOL_PROFICIENCY">
		<description>
			<p>You gain proficiency with one artisan’s tools of your choice from: smith’s tools, mason’s tools and cook’s utensils.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
			<select type="Tool Proficiency" name="Dwarf Tool Proficiency" supports="Artisan tools" number="1" />
		</rules>
	</element>
    
	<element name="Dwarf Subrace" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_DWARF_SUBRACE">
		<description>
			<p>Four subtypes are available: Forged Dwarves, Glacial Dwarves, Ironroot Dwarves and Monad Dwarves.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Dwarf Subrace" supports="Dwarf" />
		</rules>
	</element>

    <!-- Dwarf Sub Races List-->

    <!-- Forged Dwarf Sub Race-->

	<element name="Forged Dwarf" type="Sub Race" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_SUB_RACE_FORGED_DWARF">
		<supports>Dwarf</supports>
		<description>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Mortal Subtype.</em></strong> <em>Forged Dwarfs</em> are strong and well adjusted to live in warm and dry environments. Native to the Scanduri continent, these dark gray skinned smiths present red or orange eye and hair colors. Their cities are mostly found deep beneath the desert sands and far away from the demonic gate they once helped to defend. Cursed by Abyssa to lose their once great regenerative abilities, this dwarven society has withdrawn from the demonic war in fear of losing more of themselves.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Fiery Skin.</em></strong> You are immune to fire damage. Additionally, once per turn, any creature that grapples you or otherwise comes into direct contact with your skin must succeed on a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw or take 1d4 fire damage. If a creature continues to touch your skin they suffer an additional 1d4 fire damage at the start of your next turn.</p>

			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creator’s Knowledge.</em></strong> When using a weapon you crafted, if you miss an attack you may try again. You can use this feature only once per initiative and you regain this use after you roll for a new initiative.</p>
		</description>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Grants" id="ID_INTERNAL_GRANT_SUB_RACE_FORGED_DWARF"/>
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FORGED_DWARF_FIERY_SKIN" />
            <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FORGED_DWARF_CREATOR’S_KNOWLEDGE" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
    <element name="Fiery Skin" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FORGED_DWARF_FIERY_SKIN">
		<description>
			<p>You are immune to fire damage. Additionally, once per turn, any creature that grapples you or otherwise comes into direct contact with your skin must succeed on a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw or take 1d4 fire damage. If a creature continues to touch your skin they suffer an additional 1d4 fire damage at the start of your next turn.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="True">
			<description>Once per turn, any creature that grapples you or otherwise comes into direct contact with your skin must succeed on a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw or take 1d4 fire damage. If a creature continues to touch your skin they suffer an additional 1d4 fire damage at the start of your next turn.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
            <grant type="Immunity" id="ID_INTERNAL_CONDITION_DAMAGE_IMMUNITY_FIRE" />
		</rules>
	</element>
    <element name="Creator’s Knowledge" type="Racial Trait" source="Beginner's Guide" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FORGED_DWARF_CREATOR’S_KNOWLEDGE">
        <description>
            <p>When using a weapon you crafted, if you miss an attack you may try again. You can use this feature only once per initiative and you regain this use after you roll for a new initiative.</p>
        </description>
        <sheet>
            <description>When using a weapon you crafted, if you miss an attack you may try again. You can use this feature only once per initiative and you regain this use after you roll for a new initiative.</description>
        </sheet>
    </element>

	 <!-- TO:DO - REST Dwarf Sub Races List-->


</elements>
